(Yoo Yeon Seok)
(유연석)
(Esom)
(이솜)
(Kim Kyung Nam)
(김경남)
(Kim Mi Kyung, Jeon Seok Ho, Son Yeo Eun, Lee A Rin)
(김미경, 전석호, 손여은, 이아린)
(Choi Kwang Il, Jung Seung Gil, Yeon Je Hyung)
(최광일, 정승길, 연제형)
(Phantom Lawyer)
(유령 변호사)
(Supported by Ministry of Culture, Sports and KOCCA)
(문화체육관광부, 진흥원 지원)
(All people, places, and events in this drama are fictional.)
(본 드라마에 등장하는 인물, 장소, 사건은 모두 허구입니다.)
(Child actors filmed safely with guardians.)
(아역배우들은 보호자와 함께 안전하게 촬영했습니다.)
(All scenes involving animals were staged...)
(동물이 등장하는 장면은 모두 연출된 것이었습니다...)
(and filmed safely by welfare standards.)
(그리고 복지 기준에 따라 안전하게 촬영했습니다.)
(Episode 13)
(13화)
- Excuse me, where's Shin Yi Rang? - You're with Shin Yi Rang, right?
- 실례합니다. 신이랑은 어디 있나요? - 신이랑 같이 계시죠?
- Yes. - I'm so sorry.
- 예. - 정말 미안해요.
He was already unconscious when he was brought in.
그는 병원에 들어왔을 때 이미 의식을 잃은 상태였습니다.
No.
아니요.
I should've been there.
내가 거기 있었어야 했는데.
I should have been there with him.
나는 그 사람과 함께 있었어야 했어요.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
No way.
안 돼요.
Am I dead?
내가 죽었나요?
Did I...
내가...
really die?
정말 죽나요?
Mister.
아저씨.
Who are you?
누구세요?
Wait.
기다리다.
Who am I?
나는 누구입니까?
Mister.
아저씨.
You need to go that way.
그쪽으로 가야 해요.
That way?
그런 식으로요?
What's over there?
거기 뭐가 있지?
- Mother! Over here! - What?
- 어머니! 여기요! - 무엇?
Yi Rang.
이랑.
Yi Rang, Mom's here.
이랑, 엄마 왔어요.
Doctor, what's wrong with my boy? What's happening?
박사님, 제 아들에게 무슨 문제가 있나요? 무슨 일이야?
You can't go out there.
거기로는 나갈 수 없습니다.
Mister, don't go.
아저씨, 가지 마세요.
What's wrong with my boy, Doctor?
내 아들에게 무슨 문제가 있나요, 박사님?
Please, save my boy, Doctor.
제발 내 아들을 구해주세요, 박사님.
- We've tried CPR several times. - Doctor.
- 우리는 CPR을 여러 번 시도했습니다. - 의사.
Please, I'm begging you.
제발 부탁드립니다.
You promised...
약속했잖아...
you'd find my mom for me.
당신은 나를 위해 우리 엄마를 찾을 것입니다.
Patient Shin Yi Rang. Time of death, 8:43pm, August 16.
환자 신이랑. 사망 시간, 8월 16일 오후 8시 43분.
- Doctor, look! - Charge the paddles!
- 박사님, 보세요! - 패들을 충전하세요!
- Hey! Look... - Family, please step this way.
- 여기요! 보세요... - 가족 여러분, 이쪽으로 오세요.
Please step outside for a moment. Quickly, this way.
잠시 밖으로 나가주세요. 빨리, 이쪽으로.
- This way... - Clear!
- 이쪽으로... - 클리어!
Shoot.
사격.
Charge to 200.
200까지 충전하세요.
We've got a rhythm.
우리에겐 리듬이 있어요.
- Yi Rang. - Yi Rang.
-이랑. -이랑.
Can you see me? Yi Rang, are you with us?
나를 볼 수 있나요? 랑이, 우리랑 같이 있어?
Yi Rang.
이랑.
(Phantom Lawyer)
(유령 변호사)
That was Reporter Park Sung Chan.
박성찬 기자였습니다.
We will bring you more updates on the Mr. Jo case as they come in.
조씨 사건에 대한 추가 소식이 들어오는대로 전해드리겠습니다.
And now, let's meet the modern-day hero who saved young Kwon.
그리고 지금, 어린 권을 구한 현대의 영웅을 만나보자.
- Reporter Kim Bo Ra, over to you. - It's on.
- 김보라 기자, 당신에게로 갑니다. - 켜져 있어요.
Thank you. I'm reporting live from the hospital...
감사합니다. 병원에서 실시간으로 보고하고 있어요...
where Shin Yi Rang is recovering.
신이랑이 회복 중인 곳.
Shin Yi Rang sustained a gunshot wound while rescuing Kwon,
신이랑은 권씨를 구하던 중 총상을 입었고,
but he is reportedly recovering well...
하지만 그는 잘 회복하고 있다고 합니다...
- after surgery. - He's coming out.
- 수술 후. - 그 사람이 나올 거예요.
And we can see Shin Yi Rang coming out now.
그리고 이제 신이랑이 나오는 모습도 보입니다.
- Mr. Shin, just a moment! - How are you feeling?
- 신 선생님, 잠시만요! - 기분이 어때요?
- What motivated you? - Get the shot!
- 당신에게 동기를 부여한 것은 무엇입니까? - 쏴라!
- Please, just one comment! - How's your health?
- 댓글 하나만 달아주세요! - 건강은 어떤가요?
- How are you feeling? - Please, just one comment!
- 기분이 어때요? - 댓글 하나만 달아주세요!
Lightning...
번개...
power.
힘.
Power!
힘!
- Power! - Power!
- 힘! - 힘!
Lightning...
번개...
Power!
힘!
Uncle.
삼촌.
You were so awesome. The absolute best!
당신은 정말 대단했어요. 절대 최고!
- You did great. - I did?
- 정말 잘했어요. - 내가 그랬어?
If my Da Bong says I'm awesome, then I must really be awesome.
우리 다봉이가 나보고 대단하다고 하면 정말 대단한 거겠지.
That's a relief.
다행이네요.
- Be careful. - Are you okay?
- 조심하세요. - 괜찮으세요?
Get some rest, okay?
좀 쉬세요, 알았죠?
- Thanks, everyone. - See you later.
- 고마워요, 여러분. - 나중에 봐요.
Bong Soo Power!
봉수 힘내!
Yi Rang Power!
이랑 파워!
- Here. - Goodness.
- 여기. - 맙소사.
You've been through a lot. Just stay put. I'll be right back.
당신은 많은 일을 겪었습니다. 그냥 가만히 있어. 곧 돌아올게요.
Na Hyun cried?
나현이 울었어?
She said, "I should have been there with you."
그녀는 "내가 당신과 함께 있었어야 했어요"라고 말했습니다.
She said that and started crying her eyes out.
그녀는 그렇게 말하며 눈시울을 붉히며 울기 시작했습니다.
She did?
그녀가 그랬나요?
She was crying her eyes out?
그녀는 눈이 멀도록 울고 있었나요?
What are you so happy about?
당신은 무엇 때문에 그렇게 행복합니까?
Na Hyun.
나현.
Are you okay? How can you be so reckless? Especially after getting shot.
괜찮으세요? 어떻게 그렇게 무모할 수 있나요? 특히 총에 맞은 후에는요.
I'm fine. Really.
잘 지내요. 정말.
Mister, can I go to your place?
아저씨, 제가 당신 집으로 가도 될까요?
Sure. It's boring here, so go home and play with Da Bong and Grandma.
확신하는. 여기 심심하니까 집에 가서 다봉이 할머니랑 놀아주세요.
Okay! Yes!
좋아요! 예!
Si Ho's gone.
시호가 없어졌어요.
I scared you, didn't I?
내가 널 겁줬지, 그렇지?
I was scared, and I was upset.
나는 무서웠고 속상했다.
You should've taken me or your brother-in-law with you.
당신은 나나 당신의 처남을 데리고 갔어야 했어요.
Why would you go somewhere so dangerous all by yourself?
왜 이렇게 위험한 곳에 혼자 가시나요?
You're right.
당신 말이 맞아요.
I guess I got ahead of myself.
아무래도 내가 앞서 나갔던 것 같다.
I was just so desperate to find out who Si Ho was.
시호가 누구인지 알고 싶어서 너무 절실했어요.
That reminds me.
그게 생각나네요.
The day you went looking for Si Ho,
시호를 찾으러 갔던 날
his father came by the office. He wanted to talk about getting a divorce.
그의 아버지가 사무실에 오셨다. 그는 이혼에 관해 이야기하고 싶었습니다.
- A divorce? - They've been apart since Si Ho vanished.
- 이혼요? - 시호가 사라진 이후로 서로 떨어져 지냈어요.
It seemed like they were both struggling with a lot of regret and guilt.
두 사람 모두 많은 후회와 죄책감으로 힘들어하고 있는 것 같았습니다.
Plus, not knowing if Si Ho is alive or not must be even more agonizing.
게다가 시호가 살아 있는지 없는지 알 수 없다는 게 더욱 괴로울 것 같다.
That's true.
그것은 사실이다.
Sometimes a sliver of hope...
때로는 작은 희망이...
can just be another form of torture.
또 다른 형태의 고문일 수도 있다.
So, what's the status of the investigation?
그렇다면 수사 상황은 어떤가요?
Thanks to Ye Jun being rescued, we have Jo Chi Yeong in custody,
예준이 구출된 덕분에 조치영을 구금하게 되었어요
but as for Si Ho, who went missing a year ago,
하지만 1년 전 실종된 시호는
Jo Chi Yeong is pleading the fifth.
조치영이 다섯 번째 변론을 하고 있다.
Ye Jun and Si Ho are around the same age,
예준과 시호는 동갑내기,
and while it's true both kids were wearing yellow rain boots,
사실이지만 두 아이 모두 노란색 장화를 신고 있었습니다.
there's no hard evidence that Jo Chi Yeong kidnapped Si Ho.
조치영이 시호를 납치했다는 확실한 증거는 없다.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Kidnapping, false imprisonment of a child...
아동 납치, 억류...
carries a sentence of ten years at most.
최대 10년의 형을 선고받게 됩니다.
And in reality, he'll likely get a much lighter sentence.
그리고 실제로는 훨씬 가벼운 형을 선고받을 가능성이 높습니다.
How can I stand by and let that happen?
내가 어떻게 참을 수 있고 그런 일이 일어나도록 할 수 있습니까?
(Seoin Hospital)
(서인병원)
Here, put your arm around me like this.
자, 이렇게 팔을 내 주위에 두르세요.
Yi Rang got shot!
랑이 총에 맞았습니다!
Right. My bad, my bad.
오른쪽. 내 잘못이야, 내 잘못이야.
Then let's at least walk in step. Like this. Left foot, left foot.
그렇다면 적어도 한걸음씩 걷자. 이와 같이. 왼발, 왼발.
Why are we marching? This isn't the army.
우리는 왜 행진하는 걸까요? 여기는 군대가 아닙니다.
- Goodness. - Seriously!
- 맙소사. - 진지하게!
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
I slept well. Now, it's time to make the bed.
나는 잘 잤다. 이제 침대를 정리할 차례입니다.
I want to play too.
나도 놀고 싶다.
- Honey, did you sleep well? - Of course.
- 여보, 잘 잤어요? - 물론.
Now it's time for breakfast. After I eat...
이제 아침 식사 시간입니다. 식사 후에...
Honey, do you have a shoot today?
여보, 오늘 촬영 있어요?
Yes. I'm playing a doctor today.
예. 오늘은 의사 놀이를 할 거예요.
Oh my, that's so cool!
아, 정말 멋지네요!
Dad, can you please not go?
아빠, 가지 마세요?
I want to be with you.
나는 당신과 함께 있고 싶습니다.
Should we take Da Bong to the theme park this weekend?
이번 주말에 다봉이를 테마파크에 데려갈까?
Yes. That's a great idea. That's my girl.
예. 정말 좋은 생각이에요. 그 사람은 내 여자 야.
But I want to go camping.
그런데 캠핑을 가고 싶어요.
- Have a great shoot. - Okay, I will.
- 즐거운 촬영 되세요. - 알았어, 그럴게.
Excuse me. I'm here about a boy named Yoon Si Ho.
실례합니다. 저는 윤시호라는 소년 때문에 왔습니다.
Are you Si Ho's father?
시호 아버지이신가요?
You know my Si Ho?
우리 시호 알지?
I heard from the police.
경찰한테서 들었어요.
That he went missing one year ago.
그 사람이 1년 전에 실종됐다고 하더군요.
I heard you saved a boy named Ye Jun.
예준이라는 남자아이를 구했다고 들었는데
By any chance... Do you know...
혹시... 혹시 아시나요...
where my Si Ho is?
내 시호는 어디 있지?
No.
아니요.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
Hey.
여기요.
He says he doesn't know.
그는 모른다고 말합니다.
Honey... Are you okay?
여보... 괜찮아요?
Do you want me to come over now?
내가 지금 여기로 오길 바라나요?
Okay, sorry. I was just...
알았어, 미안. 난 그냥...
Our Si Ho will be okay.
우리 시호는 괜찮을 거예요.
Let's just wait a little longer.
조금만 더 기다리자.
Okay?
좋아요?
He said he'd let you ride in his police car?
그 사람이 당신을 경찰차에 태워주겠다고 했죠?
Yes.
예.
But he was a total stranger.
그러나 그는 완전히 낯선 사람이었습니다.
Weren't you scared?
두렵지 않았나요?
But I had seen him before.
하지만 나는 전에 그를 본 적이 있었습니다.
That police officer came to my school to teach a safety class.
그 경찰관이 우리 학교에 안전수업을 가르치러 왔어요.
That would've made him easier to trust.
그랬다면 그 사람을 더 쉽게 믿을 수 있었을 텐데.
And he was really nice to me.
그리고 그는 나에게 정말 친절했어요.
He even showed me his gun and played with me.
그는 심지어 나에게 총을 보여주며 나와 놀아주기까지 했습니다.
But...
하지만...
When it got dark, I told him I wanted to go home.
어두워지자 나는 그에게 집에 가고 싶다고 말했습니다.
He said we were going somewhere fun tomorrow...
내일 재미있는 곳으로 갈 거라고 하더군요...
so I should just wait.
그러니 그냥 기다려야 해요.
But I insisted on going home,
하지만 나는 집에 가야 한다고 고집했어요
and he got really mad.
그리고 그는 정말 화를 냈습니다.
Actually...
사실...
my head had been hurting since that morning,
그날 아침부터 머리가 아팠어요
but when he started yelling,
하지만 그가 소리를 지르기 시작했을 때,
my head started to hurt even more.
머리가 더욱 아프기 시작했다.
Si Ho...
시호...
Were you in a lot of pain?
많이 아팠나요?
Yes.
예.
So...
그럼...
I took some medicine and fell asleep for a long time.
약을 먹고 오랫동안 잠이 들었습니다.
And when I opened my eyes,
그리고 눈을 떴을 때,
I was in your office.
나는 당신의 사무실에있었습니다.
I see.
알겠어요.
I miss my mom and dad.
엄마 아빠가 그리워요.
Can't I go see them?
가서 볼 수는 없나요?
Si Ho.
시호.
It might be hard...
힘들 수도 있겠네요...
to see your mom and dad right now.
지금 당장 엄마 아빠를 만나러 가세요.
Why?
왜?
Because your mom and dad...
네 엄마 아빠가...
are a little sick.
조금 아파요.
Really? What's wrong with them?
정말? 그들에게 무슨 문제가 있습니까?
Their hearts are sick.
그들의 마음은 아프다.
Why?
왜?
Let's say...
가정해보자...
one of your friends fell down right next to you?
친구 중 한 명이 바로 옆에서 넘어졌나요?
How do you think you would feel?
기분이 어떨 것 같나요?
I'd feel bad.
기분이 나쁠 것 같아요.
Because I couldn't catch them.
왜냐하면 나는 그들을 잡을 수 없었기 때문이다.
Exactly.
정확히.
You know that feeling when you're sorry,
미안할 때 그 기분 아시죠,
even when it's not your fault, right?
네 잘못이 아니더라도 그렇지?
I think that's what your mom and dad are feeling.
엄마아빠도 그런 마음이실 것 같아요.
You're so precious to them,
당신은 그들에게 너무 소중해요
and they feel they couldn't protect you.
그리고 그들은 당신을 보호할 수 없다고 생각합니다.
They think, "What if I'd done this?" or "What if I'd done that?"
그들은 "내가 이런 짓을 했다면 어땠을까?"라고 생각합니다. 또는 "내가 그랬다면 어떨까요?"
And they keep blaming themselves.
그리고 그들은 계속해서 자신을 비난합니다.
That's why...
그렇기 때문에...
it's making their hearts hurt even more.
그들의 마음을 더욱 아프게 만들고 있습니다.
But they shouldn't feel that way.
하지만 그들은 그렇게 느껴서는 안 됩니다.
How does a hurting heart get better?
아픈 마음은 어떻게 나아지나요?
I just want Mom and Dad to be happy again.
나는 단지 엄마 아빠가 다시 행복해지기를 바랄 뿐입니다.
If they knew you were doing so well,
당신이 그렇게 잘하고 있다는 걸 그들이 알았다면,
don't you think they'd start to feel better?
그 사람들 기분이 나아질 것 같지 않아?
But Mom and Dad don't know that.
하지만 엄마 아빠는 그걸 모르세요.
They can't see me...
그들은 나를 볼 수 없어...
or hear from me.
아니면 내 말을 들어보세요.
Don't worry. I'll help you.
괜찮아요. 내가 도와줄게.
Okay.
좋아요.
All right then.
그럼요.
High-five.
하이파이브.
Let's go. I'll take the bag.
갑시다. 가방은 내가 맡을게.
- Just a second. Sorry. - Seriously, stop it.
- 잠깐만요. 죄송합니다. - 진짜로, 그만해요.
Okay, fine.
알았어, 알았어.
You're here early.
일찍 오셨군요.
- How are you feeling? - I'm fine. Let's get started.
- 기분이 어때요? - 잘 지내요. 시작해 봅시다.
Jo Chi Yeong left his wife for an affair...
조치영, 불륜으로 아내와 버렸다…
and was raising their son, Gyeong Seo.
아들 경서를 키우고 있었습니다.
Two years ago, while he was in the bathroom,
2년 전, 그가 화장실에 있는 동안
Gyeong Seo climbed onto a desk...
서경이 책상 위로 올라갔다...
and fell to his death after the window screen ripped.
유리창이 찢어진 후 사망했습니다.
Following the incident, his ex-wife accused him of child neglect,
사건 이후 그의 전처는 그를 아동 방치 혐의로 고발했습니다.
but the court ruled that, as a busy cop,
하지만 법원은 바쁜 경찰로서
he had not been a negligent father.
그는 태만한 아버지가 아니었습니다.
From what I hear, there doesn't seem to be anything out of the ordinary.
제가 듣기로는 별 이상은 없는 것 같습니다.
So a man who lost his child in an accident...
그럼 사고로 아이를 잃은 남자는...
goes on to kidnap and murder other children?
계속해서 다른 아이들을 납치하고 살해하나요?
So we're back to square one.
그래서 우리는 다시 원점으로 돌아왔습니다.
What evidence do we have?
우리는 어떤 증거를 갖고 있나요?
These are the crime scene photos from when Jo Chi Yeong's son fell.
조치영 아들 추락 당시 현장 사진이다.
(Crime scene photos)
(범죄 현장 사진)
(Eat pizza! Get a prize!)
(피자를 먹어라! 상품을 받아라!)
Gosh. He must have really liked pizza.
이런. 그 사람은 피자를 정말 좋아했나 봐요.
He collected a lot of coupons. He even drew his own.
그는 많은 쿠폰을 모았습니다. 그는 심지어 자신의 것을 그렸습니다.
If he was drawing fake coupons, it might not have been about the pizza.
만약 그가 가짜 쿠폰을 그리고 있었다면 피자에 관한 것이 아니었을 수도 있습니다.
He could have been trying to win one of the prizes.
그는 상 중 하나를 얻으려고 노력했을 수도 있습니다.
What were the prizes?
상금은 무엇이었나요?
- That's it. - What?
- 그게 다야. - 무엇?
Are you saying a six-year-old...
6살짜리 아이를 말하는 겁니까...
was collecting coupons for a kimchi fridge?
김치 냉장고 쿠폰을 모으고 있었나요?
No way. Hold on, let me see... When was that?
안 돼요. 잠깐만요, 어디 보자... 그게 언제였죠?
About three years ago, a local supermarket had a grand opening,
약 3년 전, 지역 슈퍼마켓이 그랜드 오픈을 했습니다.
and they had one of those big prize giveaways.
그리고 그들은 큰 경품 중 하나를 받았습니다.
My daughter, Da Bong, won the grand prize, a TV.
내 딸 다봉이가 대상인 TV를 수상했습니다.
But my Da Bong started crying.
그런데 우리 다봉이가 울기 시작했어요.
- Why? - What she really wanted...
- 왜? - 그녀가 정말로 원했던 것은...
was the fifth-place prize, a character backpack.
5위 상품은 캐릭터 백팩이었습니다.
What adults and kids value are completely different.
어른과 아이의 가치관은 전혀 다릅니다.
So if we look at this through a child's eyes...
그래서 이것을 어린이의 눈으로 본다면...
(Trip to a camp ground)
(캠프장으로의 여행)
What about this one?
이건 어때요?
That makes sense. Kids love camping.
말이 되네요. 아이들은 캠핑을 좋아합니다.
I want to go camping.
나는 캠핑을 가고 싶다.
He told me we were going somewhere fun tomorrow,
내일 재미있는 곳으로 갈 거라고 하더군요,
so he told me to just wait.
그래서 그는 나에게 기다리라고 말했습니다.
Jo Chi Yeong told Si Ho they were going somewhere fun the next day.
조치영은 시호에게 다음 날 재미있는 곳으로 간다고 말했다.
That could be the camp ground.
그곳이 캠프장일 수도 있다.
Si Ho also said Jo Chi Yeong came to his school for a safety lesson.
시호는 조치영이 학교에 안전교육을 받으러 왔다고도 밝혔다.
What if that's when Jo Chi Yeong...
그때 조치영이...
was looking for a potential target...
잠재적인 표적을 찾고 있었어요...
and was trying to give himself another chance?
그리고 자신에게 또 다른 기회를 주려고 했던 걸까요?
For the man who couldn't protect his own son?
자신의 아들을 지키지 못한 남자를 위해서?
In fact, Jo Chi Yeong called Ye Jun his son.
실제로 조치영은 예준을 아들이라고 불렀다.
And he fed Ye Jun the same kind of pizza his own son loved.
그리고 예준에게는 자신의 아들이 좋아하는 피자와 같은 종류의 피자를 먹였습니다.
So you're saying he wasn't looking for someone to get revenge on,
그럼 그가 복수할 사람을 찾고 있지 않았다는 말씀이군요,
but trying to give himself a chance to be a good father?
하지만 자신에게 좋은 아버지가 될 기회를 주려고 노력하고 있나요?
- That's completely insane. - If he planned to take Si Ho...
- 완전 미친 짓이군요. - 시호를 데려갈 생각이었다면...
to the camp ground his own son wanted to go to,
자기 아들이 가고 싶어했던 캠프장으로
it's possible he buried Si Ho there.
거기에 시호를 묻었을 가능성도 있다.
- It's possible, but that's a reach. - It's a long shot, I know.
- 가능하지만 그건 한계가 있는 일이에요. - 쉽지 않은 일이라는 걸 알아요.
That's why I'm going to meet with Jo Chi Yeong and ask him.
그래서 조치영을 만나서 물어보려고 합니다.
- Do you think he'll agree to see you? - Even if he won't see me,
- 그 사람이 당신을 만나는 데 동의할 것 같나요? - 그가 나를 보지 못하더라도
he'll want to see Si Ho.
그 사람은 시호를 보고 싶어할 거예요.
(Jo Chi Yeong)
(조치영)
(Sender: 2nd Floor, Pit-a-Pat Butcher Restaurant)
(발신자: 두근두근 정육식당 2층)
Dear Officer.
친애하는 장교.
Mister, it's me, Si Ho.
아저씨 저 시호예요.
It's Yoon Si Ho. You said you liked the back of my head.
윤시호입니다. 내 뒷머리가 마음에 든다고 했잖아.
We played a word chain game and cops and robbers,
우리는 단어 연쇄 게임과 경찰, 강도 놀이를 했어요,
and you even showed me your gun. You remember, right?
그리고 나한테 총까지 보여줬잖아. 기억나지?
If Jo Chi Yeong won't talk,
조치영이 말을 안 하면
I need you and Bong Soo to go to the camp ground...
캠프장으로 가려면 너와 봉수씨가 필요해...
and search for Si Ho.
그리고 시호를 검색해 보세요.
Got it.
알았어요.
(Good Sleeping Camp ground)
(좋은 수면 캠프장)
This is it? Just one officer?
이게 다야? 장교 한 명만요?
I had to come in on my day off.
쉬는 날에 와야 했어요.
That's because we still don't have enough evidence.
아직 증거가 충분하지 않기 때문이죠.
Still, a hero of our time is saying it. They should trust him.
그런데 우리 시대의 영웅이 이렇게 말하고 있습니다. 그들은 그를 믿어야 합니다.
Tell me about it.
그것에 대해 말해주세요.
How are we supposed to find him in a place this huge?
이렇게 큰 곳에서 어떻게 그를 찾을 수 있겠습니까?
We have to.
우리는 그래야 합니다.
With the Lord, nothing is impossible. There may only be four of us,
주님과 함께라면 불가능은 없습니다. 우리는 4명뿐일지도 몰라
but he will give us the strength of 40, or even 400 men.
그러나 그분은 우리에게 40명, 심지어 400명의 힘을 주실 것입니다.
Amen.
아멘.
All right, let me give you the rundown.
좋습니다. 간략한 내용을 알려드리겠습니다.
Plant growth is different where a body is buried...
시체가 묻힌 곳에서는 식물의 성장이 다르다...
due to the organic matter.
유기물 때문이다.
So, keep an eye out for places where...
그러니...
plants look different or are discoloured.
식물이 다르게 보이거나 변색되었습니다.
Also, I've just sent a metal detector app to your phones.
그리고 방금 귀하의 휴대폰으로 금속 탐지기 앱을 보내 드렸습니다.
Run it and hold it to the ground.
그것을 실행하고 땅에 붙드십시오.
Things like buttons, keys, or zippers will set it off right away.
버튼, 열쇠, 지퍼 등이 바로 작동됩니다.
Lawyer Han and Father,
한 변호사와 아버지,
you two take that area.
너희 둘이 그 지역을 맡아라.
The officer and I will take this side. Okay?
경찰관과 나는 이 쪽을 맡겠습니다. 좋아요?
Right.
오른쪽.
But are you a police officer by any chance?
그런데 혹시 당신이 경찰이신가요?
Let's get going.
가자.
I'll do my best.
최선을 다하겠습니다.
You again.
또 당신.
Who are you?
누구세요?
Who do you think you are,
당신은 누구라고 생각하시나요?
sending me something like that?
나한테 그런 걸 보내?
Si Ho is...
시호는...
right here with me.
바로 여기 나와 함께.
- What are you talking about? - Then how else would I know...
- 무슨 얘기를 하는 건가요? - 그럼 내가 어떻게 알겠어요...
things only you and Si Ho knew?
너랑 시호만 아는거?
Stop lying.
거짓말은 그만하세요.
- I said, stop messing with me. - You kidnapped Ye Jun and Si Ho...
- 나한테 장난치지 말라고 했잖아. - 예준과 시호를 납치한 건...
and caused Si Ho's death.
그리고 시호를 죽게 만들었다.
To anyone else, you're a shameless and heinous criminal.
다른 사람이 보기에 당신은 뻔뻔하고 흉악한 범죄자입니다.
But I...
하지만 난...
believe that Jo Chi Yeong, Gyeong Seo's father,
경서의 아버지 조치영이
might be a little different.
조금 다를 수도 있습니다.
I'm begging you.
부탁드립니다.
Gyeong Seo's father.
서경의 아버지.
Please, think of Si Ho's parents.
시호 부모님을 생각해 보세요.
They can't even find their beloved son's body,
사랑하는 아들의 시신조차 찾지 못하고,
and they've been barely living with that pain ever since.
그 이후로 그들은 그 고통을 거의 안고 살아왔습니다.
You've lost a child yourself, so you know how that feels.
당신도 아이를 잃었으니 그 기분이 어떤지 아실 겁니다.
Don't you dare run your mouth.
감히 입 다물지 마세요.
You wanted to forgive yourself, didn't you?
너 자신을 용서하고 싶었지, 그렇지?
After Gyeong Seo died,
서경이 죽은 후,
you must have been filled with regrets.
후회가 가득하셨나 봐요.
So by doing for those other kids what you couldn't do for Gyeong Seo,
그래서 서경을 위해 할 수 없었던 일을 다른 아이들을 위해 함으로써
you were telling yourself that you weren't a bad father...
당신은 나쁜 아버지가 아니라고 스스로에게 말하고 있었습니다...
- to make yourself feel better. - Shut up, you son of a gun!
- 기분이 나아지도록. - 닥쳐, 이 총잡이 자식아!
All for such a pathetic, ridiculous reason,
이 모든 것이 한심하고 터무니없는 이유로
you traumatized Ye Jun for life and caused Si Ho's death.
너는 예준에게 평생 트라우마를 안겨주고 시호를 죽게 만들었다.
- You've crushed his parents' hearts. - What do you know?
- 당신은 그의 부모님의 마음을 짓밟았습니다. - 당신은 무엇을 알고 있나요?
Oh, I know.
아, 알아요.
To a child, their parents...
아이에게는 부모가...
are their entire world.
그들의 전 세계입니다.
You took away the most precious thing they had.
당신은 그들이 갖고 있던 가장 소중한 것을 빼앗아갔습니다.
I don't know who Si Ho is.
시호가 누군지 모르겠어요.
Besides, if his parents truly loved him,
게다가 그의 부모님이 그를 진심으로 사랑했다면
they wouldn't have left him all alone.
그들은 그를 혼자 두지 않았을 것입니다.
Parents like that...
부모님이 그러시네요...
don't deserve to be parents.
부모가 될 자격이 없어.
Don't say that about my mom and dad.
우리 엄마 아빠에 대해서는 그렇게 말하지 마세요.
My mom and dad... They loved me.
우리 엄마 아빠는... 저를 사랑하셨어요.
They did everything for me.
그들은 나를 위해 모든 것을 해주었습니다.
To buy me yummy food,
맛있는 음식을 사주기 위해
my mom wouldn't buy makeup for herself.
우리 엄마는 스스로 화장품을 사지 않으셨어요.
And my dad worked late into the night...
그리고 아버지는 밤늦게까지 일하셨어요...
just to buy me pretty rain boots.
그냥 나한테 예쁜 장화를 사주려고.
They're my one and only mom and dad.
그들은 나의 하나뿐인 엄마 아빠입니다.
And I love them so, so much.
그리고 나는 그들을 너무나 사랑합니다.
I wouldn't trade them for a hundred pizzas,
난 그걸 피자 100판과 바꾸지 않을 거야,
or for the whole amusement park. I would never trade my mom and dad.
아니면 놀이공원 전체를 위해서요. 나는 결코 엄마 아빠를 바꾸지 않을 것입니다.
Mister...
아저씨...
Why are you trying to replace them?
왜 그들을 교체하려고 합니까?
I'm not your son.
나는 당신의 아들이 아닙니다.
He must have loved you so, so much too.
그 사람도 당신을 너무나 사랑했을 거에요.
If I were your son,
내가 당신의 아들이라면,
I think I'd be heartbroken.
마음이 아플 것 같아요.
Mister.
아저씨.
Why are you crying?
왜 울고 있어요?
I...
나는...
I wanted to be a good dad to Gyeong Seo.
나는 경서에게 좋은 아빠가 되고 싶었다.
I felt like it was my fault he didn't have a mom,
그 사람에게 엄마가 없는 게 내 잘못인 것 같았어요
and that I was wrong for leaving him alone.
그리고 그를 내버려둔 것은 내가 틀렸다는 것입니다.
If I could just do it over,
다시 할 수 있다면
I thought I could finally do it right.
드디어 제대로 할 수 있겠다는 생각이 들었습니다.
I didn't even know you were that sick.
나는 당신이 그렇게 아픈 줄도 몰랐어요.
I just thought you had a fever.
그냥 열이 있는 줄 알았어요.
When I came back in the morning and found you dead...
아침에 돌아와서 당신이 죽은 것을 발견했을 때...
You have no idea how shocked I was.
내가 얼마나 충격을 받았는지 당신은 모릅니다.
I'm sorry...
미안해요...
I really am so sorry.
정말 죄송해요.
If you're really sorry,
정말 미안하다면
then please take me to my mom and dad.
그럼 저를 엄마 아빠께 데려가 주세요.
Where am I right now?
나는 지금 어디에 있는가?
Move. To the right. Your right.
이동하다. 오른쪽으로. 당신의 권리.
What?
무엇?
Si Ho...
시호...
Do you think it'll be okay?
괜찮을 것 같아요?
They said they're both ready now.
이제 둘 다 준비가 되었다고 하더군요.
And Si Ho will be okay, right?
그리고 시호는 괜찮겠죠?
He's going to see how awkward things are between his parents.
그는 부모님 사이에 얼마나 어색한 일이 있는지 보게 될 것입니다.
Still, they're his mom and dad.
그래도 그들은 그의 엄마와 아빠입니다.
All right. Shall we go?
괜찮은. 갈까요?
Yes.
예.
(Rice Crackers)
(쌀과자)
Si Ho.
시호.
I was too late, wasn't I?
너무 늦었어요, 그렇죠?
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
(Run! Kitty Kindergarten)
(달려라! 고양이 유치원)
My sweet Si Ho, have you been okay?
나의 사랑 시호님 잘 지내셨나요?
Si Ho.
시호.
Mommy's here.
엄마가 여기 있어요.
You missed Mommy, didn't you?
엄마가 보고 싶었지, 그렇지?
Look at this. Look at all these flowers.
이것 좀 보세요. 이 꽃들을 보세요.
It looks like a lot of your friends stopped by.
친구들이 많이 들렀던 것 같아요.
Si Ho...
시호...
Mommy!
엄마!
- Daddy! - Si Ho!
- 아빠! - 시호!
Si Ho!
시호!
Si Ho, come here.
시호야, 이리와봐
My sweet Si Ho, there you are.
나의 사랑 시호, 거기 있었군요.
Wasn't that jump a little low?
점프가 좀 낮은거 아니었어?
I have to go now, don't I?
나 지금 가야 해, 그렇지?
How did you know?
어떻게 알았나요?
Because you look so sad.
왜냐면 당신이 너무 슬퍼 보이거든요.
But please,
하지만 제발,
don't be sad.
슬퍼하지 마십시오.
I'm so happy I got to see my mom and dad getting along before I go.
가기 전에 엄마, 아빠가 함께 지내는 모습을 볼 수 있어서 너무 기뻐요.
So...
그럼...
you should smile.
웃어야 해.
Thank you so much for everything.
모든 것에 정말 감사드립니다.
You're way cooler than Lightning Man. A hundred, a thousand times cooler.
당신은 라이트닝맨보다 훨씬 쿨해요. 백배, 천배 더 시원해요.
Me?
나?
What's so cool about me?
나의 어떤 점이 그렇게 멋진가요?
You're kind,
당신은 친절해요
handsome,
잘생겼어
and you're super weak.
그리고 당신은 매우 약해요.
Seriously... What kind of compliment is that?
진심... 무슨 칭찬이냐?
It's really hard for a weak person to save someone else.
약한 사람이 다른 사람을 구한다는 건 정말 어려운 일이다.
So I managed to do something that difficult?
그럼 내가 그렇게 어려운 일을 해냈단 말인가?
Yes, you're so cool.
네, 정말 멋지세요.
I bet your dad is really proud of you in the skies.
네 아버지는 하늘에서 너를 정말 자랑스러워하실 것 같아.
Thanks, Lightning Man.
고마워요, 라이트닝맨.
You were pretty cool yourself.
당신은 꽤 멋있었어요.
Si Ho, I...
시호, 나...
have one last gift for you.
당신을 위한 마지막 선물이 하나 있습니다.
You do?
당신은요?
One, two,
하나, 둘,
three!
삼!
Lightning Power!
번개의 힘!
- Lightning Power! - Power!
- 번개의 힘! - 힘!
Power!
힘!
Goodbye, Si Ho.
안녕, 시호.
Bye.
안녕.
Yi Rang, I'm so glad you got out so quickly.
이랑씨, 빨리 나와서 정말 다행이에요.
- Yi Rang is in great shape. - Tell me about it.
- 이랑의 ​​몸매가 아주 좋습니다. - 그것에 대해 말해 보세요.
- Thanks for the food. - Go on, eat plenty.
- 음식 고마워요. - 자, 많이 먹어라.
All right, how about a toast to Yi Rang's health?
자, 랑이의 건강을 위해 건배 어때요?
Cheers!
건배!
- Right. Da Bong should join in too. - Cheers!
- 오른쪽. 다봉이도 동참해야겠습니다. - 건배!
What?
무엇?
I said you should eat something too.
너도 뭐 좀 먹어야 한다고 했지.
Okay.
좋아요.
Don't just grill the meat. You have to eat some too.
고기만 굽지 마세요. 너도 좀 먹어야 해.
Why are you only giving food to Yi Rang?
왜 이랑한테만 음식만 주는 겁니까?
Well...
음...
Yi Rang is my only colleague, so I have to look out for him.
이랑은 나의 유일한 동료이기 때문에 내가 그를 돌봐야 한다.
Hey, now I'm starting to feel left out. I worked really hard to help too.
이봐, 이제 소외감을 느끼기 시작했어. 저도 도와주려고 정말 열심히 일했어요.
You did more than just help.
당신은 단지 도움을 준 것 이상의 일을 했습니다.
You're an indispensable part of the firm, a true asset.
귀하는 회사에 없어서는 안 될 존재이자 진정한 자산입니다.
Like our general manager?
우리 총지배인처럼요?
- Oh, my. - Right?
- 아, 이런. - 오른쪽?
Yes. The general manager.
예. 총책임자.
Wait, you're not just saying that? A real general manager?
잠깐만요, 그냥 그런 말을 하는 게 아니죠? 진짜 총지배인?
Of course! Here you go, General Manager. Let me fill your glass.
물론! 여기요, 총지배인님. 잔을 채워 드리겠습니다.
- Goodness. - To our very first General Manager...
- 맙소사. - 우리의 첫 번째 총지배인에게...
of Shin Yi Rang Law Office.
신이랑 법률사무소입니다.
- Cheers! - Cheers!
- 건배! - 건배!
Daddy's the new General Manager.
아빠가 새 총지배인이에요.
Eat up.
먹어라.
(Chairman Yang Byung Il)
(양병일 회장)
(Attorney Shin Yi Rang, key to the search for Yoon Si Ho's body...)
(신이랑 변호사, 윤시호 시신 수색의 핵심…)
(Represents victim's family in civil suit)
(민사소송에서 피해자 가족을 대리)
(Chairman Yang Byung Il)
(양병일 회장)
(He played a major role in the search for Yoon Si Ho's body.)
(윤시호 시신 수색에 큰 역할을 했다.)
(Shin Yi Rang has been confirmed to be a practising attorney.)
(신이랑 변호사가 변호사로 확정되었습니다.)
(Statement of claim for damages for torts...)
(불법행위에 대한 손해배상 청구서...)
(in the Yoon Si Ho abuse and death case)
(윤시호 학대 사망 사건)
(Taebaek)
(태백)
I told you. I have to go see Shin Yi Rang.
내가 말했잖아. 신이랑을 만나러 가야 해요.
Yes?
예?
Sir, you have some mail.
선생님, 우편물이 있어요.
- What's that one? - International mail for the Chairman.
- 저건 뭐죠? - 회장에게 보내는 국제우편물.
Give it to me. I'll take it to him.
나에게 주세요. 내가 그에게 가져갈게요.
Okay.
좋아요.
(Davith Medical Center)
(데이빗 메디컬 센터)
This is from the hospital where father had his surgery.
아버지가 수술을 하신 병원에서 찍은 사진입니다.
(To Mr. Yang Byung Il)
(양병일씨에게)
(You voluntarily stopped the treatment our medical staff recommended.)
(저희 의료진이 권고한 치료를 자발적으로 중단하셨습니다.)
(And as a result, any medical consequences that may arise...)
(그리고 결과적으로 발생할 수 있는 모든 의학적 결과...)
(are your sole responsibility.)
(그것은 전적으로 귀하의 책임입니다.)
- I should get going. - Drive safe.
- 가봐야겠어요. - 안전 운전하세요.
Come visit again soon.
곧 다시 방문하세요.
Ms. Pretty. Get home safe.
예쁜 씨. 집에 안전하게 도착하세요.
General Manager.
총책임자.
I'm going to walk Na Hyun out.
나는 나현을 데리고 나갈 것이다.
Don't bother coming back.
귀찮게 돌아오지 마세요.
Bye.
안녕.
I'm in such a great mood.
기분이 정말 좋아요.
I'm feeling good.
기분이 좋아요.
Our General Manager.
우리 총지배인.
That's right!
좋아요!
Wasn't there something you wanted to say?
하고 싶은 말은 없었나요?
About what?
무엇에 대해서?
Back at Sky Park, and at the hospital too.
스카이파크로 돌아가고, 병원으로도 돌아왔습니다.
You started to say something but never finished.
당신은 무언가 말하기 시작했지만 끝나지 않았습니다.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
It's just that at all the important moments,
단지 모든 중요한 순간에
a ghost seems to interrupt, so I was telling you to be careful.
유령이 방해하는 것 같아서 조심하라고 하더군요.
Then tomorrow...
그럼 내일...
why don't we meet somewhere even a ghost can't find us?
유령도 찾을 수 없는 곳에서 만나면 어떨까요?
We can get a good meal...
우리는 맛있는 식사를 할 수 있어요...
and say what we've been meaning to say.
그리고 우리가 말하려고 했던 것을 말해 보세요.
You have something to tell me too?
나한테도 할 말 있어?
Of course I do.
물론이죠.
I'm not in trouble, am I?
난 문제가 있는 게 아니지, 그렇지?
No, of course not.
아니요, 물론 그렇지 않습니다.
Or maybe you are.
아니면 당신이 그럴 수도 있습니다.
I am?
그래요?
What did I do this time?
이번에 내가 뭘 했지?
Come on, Na Hyun. It's better to just rip the band-aid off.
자, 나현. 그냥 반창고를 떼는 게 낫습니다.
Can't you just tell me now?
지금 나한테 말해주면 안 돼?
No.
아니요.
Why not? Please, just tell me.
왜 안 돼? 제발 말해 보세요.
Goodness.
선량.
This is way too late, but happy birthday.
너무 늦었지만 생일 축하드립니다.
I know I missed the day, but I really wanted to give this to you.
제가 그날을 놓쳤다는 걸 알지만, 저는 이것을 당신에게 꼭 주고 싶었습니다.
I can't believe I'm only giving this to you now.
내가 지금 이걸 너한테만 준다니 믿을 수가 없어.
Attorney Shin Yi Rang?
신이랑 변호사?
Yes. Attorney Han?
예. 한 변호사?
Sounds like you're out of the office.
사무실에 없는 것 같군요.
Yes. I'm getting the retainer agreement signed by Mr. Yoon Jae Uk.
예. 윤재욱 선생님의 서명을 받고 있습니다.
What are you up to, Attorney Han?
한 변호사님, 지금 무슨 일을 하고 계시나요?
CEO Kang Ji Hoon from Ideal Shoes...
아이디얼슈즈 강지훈 대표...
asked me to look over a contract for him.
나에게 그 사람의 계약서를 살펴보라고 했어요.
He's signing a new deal with an online platform.
그는 온라인 플랫폼과 새로운 계약을 체결하고 있습니다.
That's great.
훌륭해요.
We're still on for later, right?
우리 아직 나중이거든요, 그렇죠?
I texted you the location.
위치를 문자로 보내드렸습니다.
Yes, I got it.
네, 알겠습니다.
Okay, I'll be there by eight.
알겠습니다. 8시까지는 도착하겠습니다.
Okay, see you later.
좋아요, 나중에 봐요.
You seem to be in a good mood.
기분이 좋은 것 같습니다.
(Yoon Si Ho)
(윤시호)
Oh, boy. Looks like the lawyer's here.
아, 얘야. 변호사가 여기 있는 것 같군요.
(Yang Do Kyung)
(양도경)
Yes?
예?
Are you busy?
바쁘세요?
- No, Dad. - If you haven't eaten, let's eat.
- 아뇨, ​​아빠. - 안 먹었으면 먹자.
The call could not be connected. Please leave a message after the tone...
통화를 연결할 수 없습니다. 삐 소리 후에 메시지를 남겨주세요...
That's weird.
이상해요.
Where could he be?
그 사람은 어디에 있을까요?
Huh?
뭐?
You're here. I was worried when you didn't pick up.
당신은 여기 있습니다. 당신이 전화를 받지 않아서 걱정했어요.
I'm dropping the case.
사건을 기각하겠습니다.
Please leave.
떠나주세요.
- What? - Because I don't want to talk to you.
- 무엇? - 너랑 얘기하고 싶지 않으니까.
I said, leave.
나는 떠나라고 말했다.
Sir...
선생님...
Mr. Yoon, what happened?
윤 선생님, 무슨 일이 있었나요?
I'm truly grateful that you found my Si Ho,
나의 시호를 찾아주셔서 진심으로 감사드립니다
and I know very well that you've done nothing wrong.
그리고 나는 당신이 아무 잘못도 하지 않았다는 것을 잘 알고 있습니다.
But when I think about your father, I just can't stand it.
그런데 네 아버지를 생각하면 도저히 참을 수 없더라.
Because of Shin Gi Jung, my father...
신기정 때문에 아버지가...
Please, just go.
제발, 그냥 가세요.
It's been a while since we've had a meal like this, just the two of us.
이렇게 단 둘이서 식사하는 건 오랜만이에요.
You're right. When I was healthy, I was busy with work,
당신 말이 맞아요. 건강했을 때는 일하느라 바빴는데,
and when I finally had free time,
그리고 마침내 자유시간이 생겼을 때
I was away from home because I was sick.
몸이 아파서 집에 없었어요.
Now that you're healthy again,
이제 다시 건강해지셨으니
so let's do this more often, Dad.
그러니 더 자주 합시다, 아빠.
Okay.
좋아요.
Does that mean...
그 말은...
you don't have to go back to the hospital in America anymore?
이제 미국에서는 병원에 다시 갈 필요가 없나요?
The treatment is finished, so there's no reason to go back.
치료가 끝났으니 다시 갈 이유가 없습니다.
Right.
오른쪽.
Being sick taught me something.
아프다는 것은 나에게 뭔가를 가르쳐주었다.
What's most important in life.
인생에서 가장 중요한 것은 무엇입니까?
Money, fame, status... They're all meaningless.
돈, 명예, 지위... 다 무의미해요.
In the end, the only thing you have left...
결국, 당신에게 남은 유일한 것은...
is family.
가족입니다.
Your grandfather...
너의 할아버지...
never gave me a single compliment.
나에게 단 한번의 칭찬도 해주지 않았다.
He'd always ask, "Is that the best you can do?"
그는 항상 "그것이 당신이 할 수 있는 최선인가요?"라고 묻곤 했습니다.
And I would always...
그리고 나는 항상...
answer that I would work harder.
더 열심히 하겠다고 대답하세요.
Since that's how I was raised,
나는 그렇게 자랐기 때문에
I wasn't able to be very affectionate with you either.
나도 너한테 별로 다정하게 대하지 못했어.
But one thing I can say for certain...
하지만 한 가지 확실히 말할 수 있는 것은...
is that no matter what, I will protect you.
무슨 일이 있어도 내가 당신을 지켜주겠다는 것입니다.
Because that's what family does.
가족이 하는 일이니까요.
And I trust you'll do the same.
그리고 나는 당신도 똑같이 할 것이라고 믿습니다.
You trust me?
당신은 나를 신뢰합니까?
Yes.
예.
I trust my son.
나는 내 아들을 믿습니다.
Don't you worry about a thing, Dad.
아무것도 걱정하지 마세요, 아빠.
I'll protect you.
내가 당신을 보호할 것이다.
All right. Let's eat.
괜찮은. 먹자.
(Shin Yi Rang Law Office, Pit-a-Pat Butcher Restaurant)
(신이랑 법률사무소, 두근두근 정육식당)
But when I think about your father, I just can't stand it.
그런데 네 아버지를 생각하면 도저히 참을 수 없더라.
Because of Shin Gi Jung, my father...
신기정 때문에 아버지가...
(Pit-a-Pat Butcher Restaurant)
(Pit-a-Pat 정육점 레스토랑)
(Prosecutor Kim Hyun Woo)
(김현우 검사)
Yes, Prosecutor?
응, 검사님?
Lawyer Shin. I'm calling about the Yoon Jae Uk case.
신 변호사. 윤재욱 사건 때문에 전화드렸습니다.
Is now a good time to talk?
지금 이야기하기 좋은 시간인가요?
Actually, I don't think I can take that case.
사실 저는 그 사건을 맡을 수 없을 것 같아요.
Mr. Yoon Jae Uk has cancelled his retainer.
윤재욱 씨가 보유자를 취소했습니다.
What? Why is that?
무엇? 왜 그럴까요?
I'm not entirely sure.
나는 완전히 확신하지 못한다.
By any chance...
혹시...
Could you tell me what Yoon Jae Uk's father's name was?
윤재욱 아버지 성함이 무엇인지 알려주실 수 있나요?
One moment.
잠시만요.
His name was Yoon Dae Myeong. He passed away in 2003.
그의 이름은 윤대명이었다. 그는 2003년에 세상을 떠났습니다.
But why do you ask?
그런데 왜 물어보나요?
There's just something I have to find out.
꼭 알아내야 할 게 있어요.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
(Pit-a-Pat Butcher Restaurant)
(Pit-a-Pat 정육점 레스토랑)
(Yoon Dae Myeong)
(윤대명)
(Arrest warrant dismissed for Yoon Dae Myeong...)
(윤대명 구속영장 기각...)
(over child molestation charges.)
(아동 성추행 혐의에 대해.)
(Prosecutor Shin refiles warrant for Yoon in child molestation case.)
(신검사, 아동 성추행 사건 윤씨에 대한 영장 기각)
(Yoon Dae Myeong's suicide sparks backlash...)
(윤대명 자살, 반발 촉발…)
(against excessive prosecution.)
(과도한 기소에 반대합니다.)
(Corrupt prosecutor Shin Gi Jung killed in car accident.)
(신기정 비리검사 교통사고로 사망)
It's connected.
연결되었습니다.
Okay. Good work.
좋아요. 잘했어요.
I have to know what happened to protect your honour, Dad.
아버지의 명예를 지키기 위해 무슨 일이 일어났는지 알아야 해요, 아버지.
(Recycling Guide)
(재활용 안내)
What are you doing here? Shouldn't you be home?
여기서 뭐하는거야? 집에 있어야 하지 않나요?
I'm asking you, why are you out here like this?
내가 묻고 싶은 건, 당신은 왜 이렇게 나와 있는 걸까요?
I want to know the truth.
나는 진실을 알고 싶습니다.
I've read all the articles, but I still don't understand.
모든 기사를 읽었지만 여전히 이해가 되지 않습니다.
What happened to your father?
아버지는 어떻게 됐나요?
And what did my father do?
그리고 우리 아버지는 무슨 일을 하셨나요?
What's the point of digging all that up now?
지금 그걸 다 파헤치는 게 무슨 의미가 있나요?
Whether it's your father or mine.
당신의 아버지이든 내 아버지이든.
They're both long gone.
둘 다 떠난 지 오래됐어요.
I still want to know.
나는 아직도 알고 싶다.
No, I need to know.
아니, 알아야 해요.
Please.
제발.
My father was an educator.
나의 아버지는 교육자였습니다.
He was a dedicated and respected teacher...
그는 헌신적이고 존경받는 선생님이었습니다...
who won Teacher of the Year 4 times in 25 years.
25년 동안 올해의 교사상을 4번 수상했습니다.
But when he became vice principal, everything went wrong.
그러나 그가 교감이 되자 모든 것이 잘못됐다.
There was a group bullying incident at the school,
학교에서 집단 따돌림 사건이 발생했어요
and my father made the tough call of expelling the student responsible.
그리고 아버지는 책임 있는 학생을 퇴학시키라고 엄중한 명령을 내리셨습니다.
- One more time! - Good shot!
- 한 번 더! - 잘 쐈어!
The bully's parents sued my father, claiming it was excessive and biased,
가해자의 부모는 그것이 과도하고 편견적이었다고 주장하며 아버지를 고소했습니다.
but the court threw it out and ruled in his favour.
그러나 법원은 이를 기각하고 그에게 유리한 판결을 내렸습니다.
That's when the real trouble started.
그때부터 진짜 문제가 시작되었습니다.
The prosecutor on the case,
해당 사건의 검사는,
Prosecutor Shin Gi Jung, began a fishing expedition...
신기정 검사, 낚시탐험 시작…
and began indicting my father on completely unrelated charges.
전혀 관련이 없는 혐의로 아버지를 기소하기 시작했습니다.
(Shin Gi Jung)
(신기정)
Yes.
예.
All right, let's do that.
좋아요, 그렇게 합시다.
He charged him for real estate speculation over a market gain,
그는 시장 이익에 대한 부동산 투기 혐의로 그를 기소했습니다.
then charged him with embezzlement for a missing school meal receipt,
그런 다음 학교 급식 영수증 누락으로 인해 그를 횡령 혐의로 기소했습니다.
(From Incheon District Court, To Yoon Dae Myeong)
(인천지방법원에서 윤대명에게)
and even accused him of sexual harassment...
심지어 그를 성희롱 혐의로 고발하기도 했습니다...
for asking a student to fix their uniform.
학생에게 교복을 고쳐달라고 부탁한 것입니다.
(Shin Gi Jung)
(신기정)
Most of the charges were thrown out,
대부분의 혐의가 폐기되었습니다.
but the legal battles kept my father from even going to work properly.
하지만 법적 싸움으로 인해 아버지는 제대로 일을 하지도 못하셨습니다.
And with the mounting legal fees,
그리고 늘어나는 법적 비용으로
he lost the only home we had.
그는 우리가 가지고 있던 유일한 집을 잃었습니다.
But why would he go that far?
그런데 왜 그렇게까지 갈까요?
Was there some kind of history between your father and mine?
당신의 아버지와 나의 아버지 사이에 어떤 역사가 있었나요?
I wondered that myself,
나 자신도 그게 궁금했는데
but it all made sense after I talked to our lawyer.
하지만 변호사와 이야기를 나눈 후에는 모든 것이 이해가 되었습니다.
He said it's common for ex-prosecutors to land cushy jobs at law firms.
그는 전직 검사들이 로펌에 편한 일자리를 구하는 것이 흔한 일이라고 말했습니다.
The father of the student who was expelled...
퇴학당한 학생의 아버지...
was head of the country's top law firm.
국내 최고 로펌의 대표였습니다.
Prosecutor Shin Gi Jung used my father as a scapegoat.
신기정 검사는 아버지를 희생양으로 삼았다.
All for his own personal gain.
모두 자신의 개인적인 이익을 위한 것입니다.
He's the one who drove my father to his death.
그 사람은 내 아버지를 죽음으로 몰아넣은 장본인이에요.
My father...
아버지...
was found dead in a back alley in Incheon's Chinatown.
인천 차이나타운 뒷골목에서 숨진 채 발견됐다.
Half-burnt charcoal briquettes and a note were found in his car.
그의 차에서는 반쯤 탄 숯불 연탄과 쪽지 한 장이 발견됐다.
The note had just one sentence written on it.
그 쪽지에는 딱 한 문장만 적혀 있었습니다.
To my family.
내 가족에게.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
Then, three months later,
그리고 3개월 후,
my mother took her own life as well.
우리 엄마도 스스로 목숨을 끊으셨어요.
All this time,
그동안
I've completely turned a blind eye...
완전히 눈이 멀었어요...
to what my father did.
아버지가 하신 일에.
I only thought of myself and my family as the victims.
나는 나와 내 가족만 피해자라고 생각했다.
Now I realise...
이제 깨달았어...
how incredibly selfish I've been.
내가 얼마나 이기적이었는가.
I had forgotten that so many were still suffering...
나는 아직도 많은 사람들이 고통받고 있다는 사실을 잊고 있었다...
due to it.
그것 때문에.
I know an apology from me now won't change anything,
이제 나한테 사과해도 아무 것도 바뀌지 않을 거라는 걸 알아요,
but I am sincerely sorry.
하지만 진심으로 죄송합니다.
So, did you find the Shaman?
그럼 샤먼은 찾았나요?
I believe I'll be able to find him. Please give me a little more time.
나는 그를 찾을 수 있을 것이라고 믿습니다. 조금만 더 시간을 주세요.
You need to hurry.
서둘러야합니다.
If a shaman is summoning a ghost for Shin Yi Rang to meet,
무당이 신이랑을 만나기 위해 귀신을 소환한다면,
then that means he can meet that person too.
그러면 그 사람도 만날 수 있다는 뜻이에요.
That person?
그 사람?
(Shin Yi Rang, Han Na Hyun Law Office)
(신이랑, 한나현 법률사무소)
Who's there?
거기 누구 있어요?
What brings you here?
무슨 일로 여기까지 왔나요?
I didn't mean to startle you.
당신을 놀라게 하려는 의도는 아니었어요.
I apologise.
사과드립니다.
- How... - I don't really know myself.
- 어떻게... - 나 자신을 잘 모르겠어.
Something drew me here.
뭔가가 나를 여기로 이끌었습니다.
Why...
왜...
now?
지금?
It's too late.
너무 늦었어요.
I'll come back first thing in the morning.
아침에 제일 먼저 돌아올게요.
I can't take this case.
나는 이 사건을 맡을 수 없습니다.
Excuse me?
실례합니다?
I...
나는...
As for your case...
당신의 경우는...
I will not be taking it.
나는 그것을 복용하지 않을 것입니다.
(Special thanks to Choi Won Young for his guest appearance)
(게스트 출연해주신 최원영님께 특별히 감사드립니다)
(Phantom Lawyer)
(유령 변호사)
Is there a new ghost?
새로운 유령이 생겼나요?
It seems Yi Rang and that ghost don't get along.
이랑과 그 귀신은 사이가 좋지 않은 것 같아요.
- I said, why now of all times? - Do you happen to know who I am?
- 내가 말했지, 맨날 왜 지금이지? - 내가 누군지 아시나요?
You are someone who can never be forgiven.
당신은 결코 용서받을 수 없는 사람입니다.
Shin Gi Jung was the prosecutor on that case.
해당 사건의 검사는 신기정이었다.
It's late, but don't you think we should reveal the truth?
늦었지만 진실을 밝혀야 하지 않을까요?
I don't know who I am. All I know is that I'm dead.
나는 내가 누구인지 모른다. 내가 아는 건 내가 죽었다는 것뿐이다.
I'm calling because there's a ghost that needs to move on.
계속 나아가야 할 유령이 있어서 전화했어요.
- Was I that vicious? - So I'll have to send him on myself.
- 내가 그렇게 악랄했나요? - 그럼 제가 직접 보내야겠네요.
- He's gone? - Yes, he's gone.
- 그 사람이 갔나요? - 응, 그 사람은 없어졌어.
Don't blame me.
나를 비난하지 마십시오.